<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE conf-article PUBLIC "-//IEEE//IEEE Conferences JATS-based DTD v2.0//EN" "conferences.dtd">
<conf-article article-type="research" content-type="orig-research" dtd-version="2.0" open-access="no" xml:lang="eng" show-flag="show" peer-reviewed="yes" lifecycle="final" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<!-- Article Processing Date: 12/05/2025 -->
<!-- Vendor Name: Aptara -->
<!-- IEEE XML JATS Tagging Guidelines version: 20241024 -->
<!-- IEEE Math Coding Requirements and Guidelines for Vendors version: v2.4 -->
<conf-front>
<conf-proc-meta>
<conf-proc-id conf-proc-id-type="conf-acronym">EE&#x0026;AE</conf-proc-id>
<conf-proc-title-group>
<conf-full-title>2025 10th International Conference on Energy Efficiency and Agricultural Engineering (EE&#x0026;AE)</conf-full-title>
<conf-normalized-title>Energy Efficiency and Agricultural Engineering (EE&#x0026;AE), 2025 10th International Conference on</conf-normalized-title>
</conf-proc-title-group>
<volume>00</volume>
<isbn publication-format="electronic">979-8-3315-1299-6</isbn>
</conf-proc-meta>
<conf-meta>
<conf-name>2025 10th International Conference on Energy Efficiency and Agricultural Engineering (EE&#x0026;AE)</conf-name>
<conf-start iso-8601-date="2025-11-05"><day>05</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></conf-start>
<conf-end iso-8601-date="2025-11-07"><day>07</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></conf-end>
<conf-loc><city>Stara Zagora</city>, <country>Bulgaria</country></conf-loc>
</conf-meta>
<conf-article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/EEAE65901.2025.11273727</article-id>
<xplore-article-id>11273727</xplore-article-id>
<xplore-issue>11273194</xplore-issue>
<xplore-pub-id>11273191</xplore-pub-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Virtual Energy Communities in Rural Areas Through Information and Communication Technologies: Architectures and Application Models</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
<name-alternatives>
<string-name specific-use="display"><given-names>Iliyana</given-names> <surname>Ivanova</surname></string-name>
<string-name specific-use="index"><given-names>Iliyana</given-names> <surname>Ivanova</surname></string-name>
</name-alternatives>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
<name-alternatives>
<string-name specific-use="display"><given-names>Desislava</given-names> <surname>Ivanova</surname></string-name>
<string-name specific-use="index"><given-names>Desislava</given-names> <surname>Ivanova</surname></string-name>
</name-alternatives>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution content-type="institution">Konstantin Preslavsky University of Shumen Shumen</institution>
</institution-wrap>
, <country>Bulgaria</country> \\ <email>i.s.ivanova@shu.bg</email></aff>
<aff id="aff2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution content-type="institution">Konstantin Preslavsky University of Shumen \\ Shumen</institution>
</institution-wrap>
, <country>Bulgaria</country> \\ <email>d.n.ivanova@shu.bg</email></aff>
<pub-date date-type="cover" pub-type="print" iso-8601-date="2025-11-07"><day>7</day><month>Nov.</month><year>2025</year></pub-date>
<fpage>***</fpage>
<lpage>***</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>979-8-3315-1299-6 &#x00A9; 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining, and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See <uri>https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html</uri> for more information.</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2025</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder copyright-owner="IEEE"></copyright-holder>
<license license-type="IEEE">
<ali:license_ref></ali:license_ref>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="xml">11273727_ft.xml</self-uri>
<self-uri content-type="print">30.pdf</self-uri>
<abstract xml:lang="en">
<p>This paper examines Virtual Energy Communities (VECs) as a tool for sustainable energy transition and rural development. The main characteristics of VECs are presented, including the prosumer model, P2P energy trading, smart contracts, and flexible consumption. Three main architectures-centralized, decentralized, and hybrid-are analyzed together with their supporting ICT technologies such as IoT, edge computing, artificial intelligence, blockchain, and modern communication standards. The study summarizes international practices from the EU, North America, and Asia, identifying the social, technological, and regulatory factors driving the implementation of VECs. For Bulgaria, the opportunities are linked to European funding mechanisms and national strategies for digitalization and artificial intelligence. A mathematical optimization model is proposed to balance generation, storage, and consumption, with practical applications in rural and industrial regions. Challenges related to infrastructure, regulation, and cybersecurity are outlined. Recommendations are provided for future research and policies to support the development of VECs in Bulgaria within the framework of the European Green Deal.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="AuthorFree">
<kwd>Virtual Energy Communities</kwd>
<kwd>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</kwd>
<kwd>Decentralized Energy</kwd>
<kwd>Renewable Energy Sources (RES)</kwd>
<kwd>Mathematical Models</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="2"/>
<table-count count="0"/>
<equation-count count="1"/>
<ref-count count="15"/>
<page-count count="0"/>
</counts>
</conf-article-meta>
</conf-front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1">
<label>I.</label>
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Rural areas in Europe and around the world are increasingly facing new challenges related to energy independence, sustainability and access to developed energy infrastructure. These regions have an outdated energy grid, high energy costs and limited opportunities to participate in the energy transition - the process of moving towards a lowcarbon economy using renewable energy sources and modern energy solutions. Meanwhile, renewable energy sources (RES) such as solar, wind and biomass provide opportunities for decentralization and clean electricity generation, especially in agrarian areas. Maximizing the potential of these opportunities entails adopting organizational, coordination, and energy management models that surpass conventional centralized systems. The concept of Virtual Energy Communities has emerged as a progressive model for decentralized energy cooperation that, through information and communication technologies, allows the co-production, sharing, trading, and optimization of energy between individual consumers and producers without being geographically constrained.</p>
<p>VECs offer a real response to the global sustainable energy goals set out in the European Green Deal and the UN Sustainable Development Goals. Through the integration of IoT, blockchain, artificial intelligence and smart grid technologies, VECs contribute to building more sustainable and intelligent energy systems that can meet the specific needs of rural areas.</p>
<p>This paper aims to present existing technological and organizational solutions related to VECs, to summarize best practices and models from international experience and to outline the potential for their implementation in rural Bulgaria. The role of ICT is highlighted in overcoming infrastructural and socio-economic barriers that limit the development of energy communities in the country.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2">
<label>II.</label>
<title>Virtual Energy Communities: Components and Architectures</title>
<p>VECs are collections of individuals and entities that are connected through digital infrastructure and interact with each other to produce, consume and manage energy more efficiently. Compared to conventional energy networks, VECs offer a model of decentralization where individual actors are not only consumers but active parties in the energy system. The main activities within VECs include production, sharing and trading and coordination and optimization. These communities are built on the principles of digitalization and smart governance, enabling the participation of diverse users-households, farmers, Small and Medium-sized Enterprises (SMEs), and municipalities. The main components of VECs include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Prosumer model - each participant is both a producer and consumer of energy, which promotes autonomy and reduces dependence on centralized suppliers.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Peer-to-Peer (P2P) energy trading - participants can directly buy and sell energy with each other through decentralized platforms.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Smart Contracts - automation of energy transactions through blockchain technology, ensuring transparency and security of contractual relationships.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Demand Response - adapting consumption in real time according to production, market conditions and grid needs, through automated systems and smart devices.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Collective storage - the use of shared energy storage systems (batteries) that optimize the balance between production and consumption within a community.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Intelligent data management - systems for collecting, analyzing and predicting consumer energy behavior, supported by artificial intelligence and big data analytics.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
<label>Fig. 1.</label>
<caption><p>The main components of virtual energy communities</p></caption>
<graphic position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="11273727-fig-1-source.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The architecture of VECs defines how the interaction between participants, energy exchange and data processing is organized. Three main types of architecture are distinguished in the literature:
<list list-type="ordered">
<list-item><label></label><p>Centralized architecture - in this model, the community is managed through a central operator or platform that coordinates all energy flows, transactions and balancing between producers and consumers. The centralized structure facilitates connection to the national power system. It allows for tight control over security and compliance with regulatory requirements. This approach is particularly suitable for small communities with a limited number of participants or in regions where regulations and technical infrastructure do not allow for full decentralization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">[1]</xref>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label></label><p>Decentralized architecture - relies on blockchain technologies and P2P platforms where there is no central intermediary. Each participant can directly transact with other community members through smart contracts, ensuring security and automation. This model is suitable for communities with high digital literacy and infrastructure readiness to implement distributed ledger technologies (DLT). Despite the advantages, challenges are related to energy efficiency of blockchain networks and the need for reliable communication connectivity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">[2]</xref>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label></label><p>Hybrid architecture - this model combines the advantages of centralized and decentralized management. In this case, there is a central controlling authority or platform, but it allows decentralized transactions between participants based on blockchain technologies. Hybrid architecture is preferred when there is a need to ensure regulatory compliance and at the same time exploit the advantages of P2P markets and smart contracts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">[3]</xref>.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>The types of virtual energy community architecture are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>:
<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
<label>Fig. 2.</label>
<caption><p>Virtual energy community architecture</p></caption>
<graphic position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="11273727-fig-2-source.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>The development of VECs would be impossible without the use of advanced ICT components that support the construction and operation of VECs. These include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Internet of Things (IoT) - provides a network of interconnected sensors and devices that monitor real-time energy production, consumption and storage. This enables efficient tracking of the energy contributions of each community actor.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Edge Computing - an approach to local data processing that allows decisions to be made close to where the information is generated, rather than sending the data to remote cloud servers. This significantly reduces latency and increases security. The application of edge computing in microgrids improves energy management and provides stability to local power systems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">[4]</xref>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Big Data Analytics - The large volumes of data generated within VECs require powerful analytical tools. Big Data analytics supports forecasting and the identification of energy patterns to enhance the allocation of energy resources. Big Data plays a crucial role in the transformation of smart grids by providing more accurate predictions and enabling strategic resource management <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">[5]</xref>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Artificial Intelligence (AI) and Machine Learning (ML) - these technologies automate processes, offering intelligent strategies for renewable generation forecasts. There are models based on real data that use AI to manage energy communities and improve their efficiency <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">[6]</xref>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Blockchain - technology can facilitate P2P trading in microgrids through smart contracts, increasing the security and efficiency of energy exchange processes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">[7]</xref>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Long Range Wide Area Network (LoRaWAN) communications - LoRaWAN is a wireless communication protocol designed specifically for long-range, low-power IoT networks. As a result, LoRaWAN allows building affordable and sustainable communication networks without the need for expensive mobile or wired infrastructure. This protocol proves to be effective in both rural and urban settings <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">[8]</xref>. IoT systems often use communication protocols such as Message Queuing Telemetry Transport (MQTT), which provide realtime data transmission with minimal power consumption - an advantage for devices operating in remote areas with limited resources <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">[9]</xref>. At the same time, 5 G networks provide the high speed and low latency needed for applications with critical time and capacity requirements <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">[10]</xref>.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>These components form the technological basis of VECs and enable their sustainable integration into modern energy systems.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3">
<label>III.</label>
<title>Global Overview of Virtual Energy Communities</title>
<p>VECs are being widely developed and implemented across various regions of the world, adapting to local energy policies and regulatory frameworks. The European Union has led the way in creating a regulatory framework for the development of energy communities through the Renewable Energy Directive (RED II), which defines the concept of energy communities and encourages the participation of citizens, small businesses and local authorities in energy production, consumption and trade <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">[11]</xref>. An example of a successful national policy is Energiewende in Germany, where energy cooperatives and communities are key to the transition to a low-carbon economy. Germany is also implementing decentralized P2P trading platforms and local markets <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">[12]</xref>.</p>
<p>In the US, the Brooklyn Microgrid in New York is one of the first real examples of a decentralized energy community based on a blockchain P2P trading platform. In this model, participants can directly buy and sell energy from and to their neighbors, and the process is fully automated through smart contracts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">[7]</xref>.</p>
<p>In Asia, Japan is actively investing in building smart energy communities integrating IoT and AI to manage local microgrids and optimize consumption. Cities such as Fukuoka are implementing digital twins and AI for load balancing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">[13]</xref>.</p>
<p>In South Korea, blockchain technologies are being used to build decentralized energy trading platforms, facilitating the integration of large numbers of prosumers into the national energy grid. There, the government is actively supporting pilot projects for virtual energy communities in smart cities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">[14]</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4">
<label>IV.</label>
<title>Challenges and Constraints</title>
<p>Despite the many advantages, the development of virtual energy communities is associated with several challenges and limitations that may hinder their widespread implementation and sustainability.
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Technology challenges - include the complexity of integrating diverse renewable energy solutions. Another challenge is the coordination of energy storage and smart grid systems within a unified platform. The need for highly reliable communication infrastructures and the complexity of managing large volumes of data in real time make it difficult for VECs to operate effectively. Furthermore, the lack of standardized technology solutions and protocols can limit interoperability between different systems and devices.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Economic and social barriers - expressed in the need for significant upfront investment to build infrastructure, deploy IoT devices, storage systems and commerce platforms. Social challenges include lack of awareness and engagement among citizens, and reluctance to participate in energy communities due to lack of trust or understanding of the benefits.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Regulatory constraints - in many countries the regulatory framework is still insufficiently developed to fully support the development of VECs. The lack of clear rules on energy trading, sharing and taxation of prosumers creates uncertainty and hinders investment. There are also constraints related to access to energy markets and a lack of incentives for small producers, making participation in such communities less attractive.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>The integration of modern digital technologies introduces new cybersecurity challenges. It leads to a higher risk of cyber-attacks and unauthorized access. Additionally, there is an increased threat of personal and energy data being misused. This involves ensuring that sensitive data remains protected from unauthorized access, remains unaltered during transmission or storage, and is only available to the appropriate users. The lack of standardized cybersecurity solutions in the energy community is a significant barrier to their wider adoption <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">[3]</xref>. These challenges highlight the need for coordinated efforts between technology companies, policies, regulators, and the communities themselves to find sustainable solutions for the development of VECs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5">
<label>V.</label>
<title>Opportunities and Prospects for Bulgaria</title>
<p>In Bulgaria, the development of Virtual Energy Communities faces challenges due to the lack of a legal definition and limited examples of energy cooperation. Nevertheless, the country possesses natural and technological conditions favorable for implementing VECs, particularly in regions with high solar radiation and renewable energy potential. Climate change is expected to impact biodiversity, water resources, agriculture, and forests, which will have negative effects on society, citizens, and the economy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">[15]</xref>. This necessitates the integration of sustainable energy solutions.</p>
<p>The development of virtual energy communities in Bulgaria combines significant potential with the need for targeted policies, technical infrastructure, and social engagement. Although the concept is not yet formally defined in Bulgarian legislation, several prerequisites provide a favorable foundation for their implementation.</p>
<p>Currently, there are only a few examples of energy cooperation in Bulgaria, mainly through associations for photovoltaic installations or energy efficiency initiatives. The lack of a clearly defined legal framework for "energy communities" and the absence of incentives for peer-to-peer energy trading limit the widespread adoption of VECs. Additionally, rural areas still experience insufficient digital connectivity and low levels of digital literacy.</p>
<p>The sustainable development of energy communities depends on the presence of supportive conditions established by both policy and infrastructure. Without a stable regulatory environment and mechanisms that ensure long-term viability, such initiatives face significant challenges. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">[1]</xref>. In this regard, Bulgaria should:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Adequately transpose RED II into national legislation with a focus on decentralized citizen participation.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Legally define the concept of a "virtual energy community".</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Facilitate access to the energy grid for prosumers.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Introduce incentives for investments in digital platforms for managing VECs.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>Bulgaria has access to a range of European and national programs that support the development of virtual energy communities. These include The LIFE Clean Energy Transition program, Horizon Europe - Cluster 5, the Recovery and Resilience Facility, and the Rural Development Program, which provide funding for the decentralization of energy systems, digitalization, renewable energy sources, and agroenergy communities. These mechanisms create favorable conditions for energy development and increased energy independence in rural areas. Leveraging all these instruments can accelerate the implementation of VECs in Bulgariaespecially considering the EU Green Deal, the need for energy independence, and the opportunities for digital transformation of the energy sector.</p>
<p>For the effective implementation of virtual energy communities, it is essential to:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Invest in communication infrastructure (LoRaWAN, 5G).</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Develop open-source platforms for energy flow management and trading.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Promote training programs and digital skills development for local communities.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Introduce software solutions based on AI and blockchain to support management, forecasting, and data security.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>The use of mathematical models and visualizations is an important element in the planning and management of VECs. These tools support the understanding and forecasting of the dynamics between energy production, consumption, storage, and trading, as well as informed decision-making for governance.</p>
<p>Applying mathematical models to optimize energy flows within VECs in Bulgaria can contribute to more efficient use of local resources and a reduction in energy dependence. A basic mathematical approach is illustrated by the following formula:
<disp-formula id="deqn1"><tex-math notation="LaTeX">\begin{equation*}
\text { Minimize } C=\sum_{t=1}^{T}\left(C_{\text {gen }}(t)+C_{\text {stor }}(t)+C_{\text {exch }}(t)\right)
\tag{1}
\end{equation*}</tex-math></disp-formula></p>
<p>Where:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>C - total system costs for energy management.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p><inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$\mathrm{C}_{\text {gen }}(\mathrm{t})$</tex-math></inline-formula> - cost of energy generation at time t.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p><inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$\mathrm{C}_{\text {stor }}(\mathrm{t})$</tex-math></inline-formula> - cost of energy storage and transfer at time t.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p><inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$\mathrm{C}_{\text {exch }}(\mathrm{t})$</tex-math></inline-formula> - cost associated with energy exchange with the external grid and among participants at time t.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>T - total number of time intervals.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>This objective function is formulated to optimally balance energy production, storage, and trading within VECs, considering temporal dynamics.</p>
<p>The mathematical model presented in equation~(\ref{eqn1}) can be applied by collecting data on the costs of generation, storage, and exchange. Optimization algorithms then minimize the total system cost and determine whether it is more advantageous for the energy to be consumed, stored, or sold. In Bulgaria, this model is particularly suitable for agricultural regions such as Dobruja and the Thracian plain. It can also be applied in municipalities of the Rhodopes and the Northwestern region with outdated electrical grid, as well as in industrial zones and tourist areas. In these cases, balancing local generation, storage, and consumption improves energy autonomy and reduces dependence on the centralized grid. The model can assist municipalities and cooperatives in effective planning with limited resources by guiding investments in energy generation and trading. It also facilitates integration with the European energy market and supports the green transition by accounting for the carbon footprint of energy flows. Implementing this model in pilot projects for VECs and microgrids would promote long-term growth and enhance regional energy balance.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6">
<label>VI.</label>
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The future of Virtual Energy Communities in Bulgaria and globally requires a systematic scientific approach that encompasses both technological and economic aspects. To fully realize the potential of VECs, research should focus on the development of platform-based solutions that integrate IoT devices, edge computing, blockchain, and artificial intelligence into a unified environment for energy flow management. It is essential that these platforms offer userfriendly access to P2P energy trading.</p>
<p>The use of simulations and digital twins is a primary tool for modeling energy communities. These technologies allow for forecasting system behavior, managing loads, and assessing resilience under various scenarios. Cybersecurity is another major challenge in the digitalization of energy systems, necessitating the deployment of advanced protection protocols to prevent potential attacks.</p>
<p>In Bulgaria, the application of mathematical models for optimizing energy flows can support the strategic planning of VECs, enable optimal allocation of generated energy among consumption, storage, and trading, and improve forecasting based on seasonal fluctuations in renewable energy output. Bulgarian research institutes and universities have the capacity to adapt these methods to national conditions, including regional differences in consumption patterns and resource availability.</p>
<p>In the long term, implementing such models and technologies will contribute to the development of intelligent energy systems in Bulgaria, aligned with the goals of the European Green Deal and the evolving EU energy market.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7">
<label>VII.</label>
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Virtual Energy Communities represent an effective organizational and technological approach to restructuring energy systems, particularly in rural areas. By combining renewable energy sources with modern digital technologies such as IoT, artificial intelligence, blockchain, and edge computing, VECs enable improved management of local generation, storage, and consumption. The analysis of architecture and ICT components highlights the potential of centralized, decentralized, and hybrid models, as well as the importance of secure and efficient data exchange through contemporary communication standards.</p>
<p>The application of mathematical models for energy flow optimization in Bulgaria can support agricultural regions, municipalities, industrial zones, and tourist areas in achieving greater energy autonomy. The proposed model demonstrates how general reduced storage, and exchange costs can be minimized to increase energy efficiency, reduce dependence on the centralized grid, and facilitate integration with the European energy market. By accounting for the carbon footprint of energy flows, the model also contributes to the objectives of the green transition.</p>
<p>The successful implementation of VECs requires not only technological infrastructure but also supportive policies, financial mechanisms, and initiatives for capacity building at the local level. Pilot projects in rural regions of Bulgaria can serve as experimental environments for validating the proposed models and strategies. In the long term, the integration of VECs into the national energy system has the potential to strengthen regional economies and align Bulgaria with the goals of the European Green Deal.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack><title>Acknowledgment</title>
<p>The authors gratefully acknowledge the support provided by the project CoE UNITe BG16RFPR002-1.014-0004 funded by PRIDST, co-funded by the European Union. This study was supported by internal research project RD-08109/05.02.2025 funded by Konstantin Preslavsky University of Shumen.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="ref1"><label>[1]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>S.</given-names> <surname>Akbar</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M. A.</given-names> <surname>Khan</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M.</given-names> <surname>Bilal</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>B.</given-names> <surname>Jamil</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>A Review of Renewable Energy Communities: Concepts, Scope, Progress, Challenges, and Recommendations</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>Sustainability</source>, vol. <volume>16</volume>, no. <issue>5</issue>, p. <fpage>1749</fpage>, <month>Feb.</month> <year>2024</year>. [Online]. Available: <uri>https://www.mdpi.com/</uri><fpage>2071</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1050</lpage>/16/5/1749.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref2"><label>[2]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>F.</given-names> <surname>Rossi</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>L.</given-names> <surname>Fumagalli</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>E.</given-names> <surname>Pons</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>Renewable Energy Communities: Towards a new sustainable model of energy production and sharing</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>Energy Strategy Reviews</source>, vol. <volume>55</volume>, p. <fpage>101522</fpage>, <year>2024</year>. [Online]. Available: <uri>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.esr.2024.101522</uri></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref3"><label>[3]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="online" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"> EnergyREV</person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>ICT Infrastructure Supporting Smart Local Energy Systems</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>EnergyREV Insights</source>, <year>2021</year>. [Online]. Available: <uri>https://www.energyrev.org.uk/media/1453/ict-infrastructure-supporting-smart-local-energy-systems.pdf</uri>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref4"><label>[4]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="online" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>H.</given-names> <surname>Wang</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>Edge computing and hybrid control technology for microgrids</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>IET Smart Grid</source>, <year>2023</year>. [Online]. Available: <uri>https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1049/enc2.12103</uri></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref5"><label>[5]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>Y.</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>T.</given-names> <surname>Huang</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>E. F.</given-names> <surname>Bompard</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>Big data analytics in smart grids: a review</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>Energy Informatics</source>, vol. <volume>1</volume>, no. <issue>8</issue>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>24</lpage>, <month>Dec.</month> <year>2018</year>.\\ [Online]. Available: <uri>https://energyinformatics.springeropen.com/articles/10.1186/s42162-018-0007-5</uri>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref6"><label>[6]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="online" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>A.</given-names> <surname>Rashid</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>P.</given-names> <surname>Biswas</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A.</given-names> <surname>Biswas</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M. A.</given-names> <surname>Al</surname></string-name> Nasim, <string-name><given-names>K. D.</given-names> <surname>Gupta</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>R.</given-names> <surname>George</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>Present and Future of AI in Renewable Energy Domain: A Comprehensive Survey</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>arXiv preprint</source>, arXiv:2406.16965, <month>Jun.</month> <year>2024</year>. [Online]. Available: <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16965</uri></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref7"><label>[7]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="online" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>G.</given-names> <surname>Vieira</surname></string-name> and <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>Peer-to-Peer Energy Trading in a Microgrid Leveraged by Smart Contracts</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>arXiv</source>, <month>Dec.</month> <year>2021</year>. [Online]. Available: <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/2201.04944</uri>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref8"><label>[8]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>N.</given-names> <surname>Buli&#x0107;</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>L.</given-names> <surname>Ga&#x0161;par</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M.</given-names> <surname>Perkovi&#x0107;</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>I.</given-names> <surname>Ljubi</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>LoRa-Based IoT Network Assessment in Rural and Urban Scenarios</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>Sensors</source>, vol. <volume>23</volume>, no. <issue>3</issue>, p. <fpage>1695</fpage>, <month>Feb.</month> <year>2023</year>. [Online]. Available: <uri>https://www.mdpi.com/</uri><fpage>1424</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8220</lpage>/23/3/1695</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref9"><label>[9]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>S.</given-names> <surname>Stoyanov</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Z.</given-names> <surname>Kuzmanova</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>T.</given-names> <surname>Stoyanova</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>Weather Monitoring System Using IoT-based DIY Automatic Weather Station</article-title>,&#x201D; in Proc. <year>2024</year> 9th Int. Conf. Energy Efficiency and Agricultural Engineering (EE&#x0026;AE), Ruse, Bulgaria, <month>Jun.</month> <year>2024</year>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref10"><label>[10]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="online" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>E.</given-names> <surname>Demir</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>Low-Power 5G Protocols for Sustainable Communication in Rural Areas</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>Eur. J. Electr. Commun. Eng.</source>, <year>2024</year>. [Online]. Available: <uri>https://ejece.org/index.php/ejece/article/view/676</uri>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref11"><label>[11]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>European</given-names> <surname>Parliament</surname></string-name></person-group> and the Council of the European Union, &#x201C;<article-title>Directive (EU) <year>2018</year>/2001 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 11 <month>December</month> <year>2018</year> on the promotion of the use of energy from renewable sources (recast)</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>Official Journal of the European Union</source>, vol. L 328, pp. <fpage>82</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>209</lpage>, Dec. <year>2018</year>. [Online]. Available: <uri>https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legalcontent/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:3</uri><year>2018</year>L2001.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref12"><label>[12]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>T.</given-names> <surname>Bauwens</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>B.</given-names> <surname>Gotchev</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>L.</given-names> <surname>Holstenkamp</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>What drives the development of community energy in Europe? The case of wind power cooperatives</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>Energy Research &#x0026; Social Science</source>, vol. <volume>13</volume>, pp. 136147, <month>Mar.</month> <year>2016</year>. Available: <uri>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.erss.2015.12.016</uri></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref13"><label>[13]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="online" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>T.</given-names> <surname>Cioar&#x0103;</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>I.</given-names> <surname>Anghel</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M.</given-names> <surname>Antal</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>I.</given-names> <surname>Salomie</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>C.</given-names> <surname>Antal</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>G. I. A.</given-names> <surname>Arcas</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>An Overview of Digital Twins Application Domains in Smart Energy Grid</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>arXiv preprint</source>, arXiv:2104.07904, <month>Apr.</month> <year>2021</year>. [Online]. Available: <uri>https://arxiv.org/abs/2104.07904</uri></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref14"><label>[14]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>O. O.</given-names> <surname>Tooki</surname></string-name> and <string-name><given-names>O. M.</given-names> <surname>Popoola</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>A Systematic Review on BlockchainBased Energy Trading in a Decentralized Transactive Energy System: Opportunities, Complexities, Strategic Challenges, Research Directions</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>Results in Engineering</source>, vol. <volume>27</volume>, p. <fpage>106237</fpage>, <month>Jul.</month> <year>2025</year>. [Online]. Available: <uri>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rineng.2025.106237</uri>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref15"><label>[15]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>D.</given-names> <surname>Dimanova</surname></string-name> and <string-name><given-names>Z.</given-names> <surname>Kuzmanov</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>Assessment of Climatic Risks and Expected Impacts for the Territory of Bulgaria</article-title>,&#x201D; in <source>Proc. 9th Int. Conf. Energy Efficiency and Agricultural Engineering (EE&#x0026;AE)</source>, Ruse, Bulgaria, <month>Jun.</month> <year>2024</year>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>

</back>
</conf-article>