<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE conf-article PUBLIC "-//IEEE//IEEE Conferences JATS-based DTD v2.0//EN" "conferences.dtd">
<conf-article article-type="research" content-type="orig-research" dtd-version="2.0" open-access="no" xml:lang="eng" show-flag="show" peer-reviewed="yes" lifecycle="final" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<!-- Article Processing Date: 12/05/2025 -->
<!-- Vendor Name: Aptara -->
<!-- IEEE XML JATS Tagging Guidelines version: 20241024 -->
<!-- IEEE Math Coding Requirements and Guidelines for Vendors version: v2.4 -->
<conf-front>
<conf-proc-meta>
<conf-proc-id conf-proc-id-type="conf-acronym">SITA</conf-proc-id>
<conf-proc-title-group>
<conf-full-title>2025 International Conference on Intelligent Systems: Theories and Applications (SITA)</conf-full-title>
<conf-normalized-title>Intelligent Systems: Theories and Applications (SITA), 2025 International Conference on</conf-normalized-title>
</conf-proc-title-group>
<volume>00</volume>
<isbn publication-format="electronic">979-8-3315-5989-2</isbn>
</conf-proc-meta>
<conf-meta>
<conf-name>2025 International Conference on Intelligent Systems: Theories and Applications (SITA)</conf-name>
<conf-start iso-8601-date="2025-10-20"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></conf-start>
<conf-end iso-8601-date="2025-10-21"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></conf-end>
<conf-loc><city>Rabat</city>, <country>Morocco</country></conf-loc>
</conf-meta>
<conf-article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/SITA67914.2025.11273689</article-id>
<xplore-article-id>11273689</xplore-article-id>
<xplore-issue>11273192</xplore-issue>
<xplore-pub-id>11273189</xplore-pub-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Towards Natural Representation of User Preferences: a Graph Neural Network Approach to Recommender Systems</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
<name-alternatives>
<string-name specific-use="display"><given-names>Khaoula</given-names> <surname>BELAROUI</surname></string-name>
<string-name specific-use="index"><given-names>Khaoula</given-names> <surname>BELAROUI</surname></string-name>
</name-alternatives>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
<name-alternatives>
<string-name specific-use="display"><given-names>Habib</given-names> <surname>AYAD</surname></string-name>
<string-name specific-use="index"><given-names>Habib</given-names> <surname>AYAD</surname></string-name>
</name-alternatives>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution content-type="institution">2IACS - ENSET \\ Hassan II University of Casablanca \\ Mohammedia Morocco \\ <email>khaoula.belaroui-etu@etu.univh2c.ma</email></institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution content-type="institution">2IACS - ENSET \\ Hassan II University of Casablanca \\ Mohammedia Morocco \\ <email>habib.ayad@univh2c.ma</email></institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<pub-date date-type="cover" pub-type="print" iso-8601-date="2025-10-21"><day>21</day><month>Oct.</month><year>2025</year></pub-date>
<fpage>***</fpage>
<lpage>***</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>979-8-3315-5989-2 &#x00A9; 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining, and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See <uri>https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html</uri> for more information.</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2025</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder copyright-owner="IEEE"></copyright-holder>
<license license-type="IEEE">
<ali:license_ref></ali:license_ref>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="xml">11273689_ft.xml</self-uri>
<self-uri content-type="print">1014339.pdf</self-uri>
<abstract xml:lang="en">
<p>The majority of conventional recommender systems are based on superficial similarities, explicit user profiles or ratings, and fail to model the underlying structure of user-item relationships.</p>
<p>In this paper, we illustrate how Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) offer a more natural and principled way to represent such relationships by exploiting the intrinsic graph structure of recommendation data. We compare three paradigms on the MovieLens 100k dataset: Matrix Factorization (MF), memorybased Collaborative Filtering (CF), and a GNN model. Both users and items are nodes in a bipartite graph in our model. Through the use of SAGEConv layers, the GNN incorporates contextual information from the neighborhood of a node in order to produce more expressive and structure-aware embeddings. Ratings of users are output in a regression task by a multilayer perceptron.</p>
<p>Our results show that the GNN model outperforms MF and CF across all splits with RMSE below 1.0. Our study shows the value of using graph structure as an inductive bias and charts a way to recommender system design, away from surface similarity and toward relational, deeper knowledge.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="AuthorFree">
<kwd>Graph Neural Networks &#x2022; Recommender Systems &#x2022; Matrix Factorization &#x2022; Collaborative Filtering &#x2022; Graph Representation Learning &#x22C5; MovieLens &#x22C5; Bipartite Graph &#x22C5; Regression</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="4"/>
<table-count count="1"/>
<equation-count count="5"/>
<ref-count count="17"/>
<page-count count="0"/>
</counts>
</conf-article-meta>
</conf-front><pt><front>
\DeclareUnicodeCharacter{22C5}{\ifmmode\cdot\else{$\cdot$}\fi}
</front></pt>
<body>
<sec id="sec1">
<label>I.</label>
<title>Introduction: from Shallow Heuristics to Graph-Based Representation Learning</title>
<p>Recommendation systems have become an invisible compass in our digital lives - influencing what we watch, read, buy, and even whom we follow. As these systems evolved, so did the methods behind them: from hand-crafted heuristics to latent vector models, and now to architectures capable of learning directly from the relational structure of user-item interactions.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref> offers a conceptual overview of this evolution. Historically, collaborative filtering (CF) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">[1]</xref> techniques were divided into two branches: memory-based methods (userbased or item-based), which relied on similarity metrics; and model-based methods, including matrix factorization (MF) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">[2]</xref>, which sought to uncover hidden patterns in rating matrices. Before the rise of Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">[9]</xref>, several "shallow" graph-based methods - such as DeepWalk <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">[7]</xref>,</p>
<p>Node2Vec <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">[8]</xref> - introduced the idea of leveraging network topology, but they lacked end-to-end learning and suffered from limited task-specific generalization.</p>
<p>A common feature of most traditional approaches is their reliance on Euclidean spaces: users and items are represented as vectors in flat geometry, and interactions are captured through inner products or similarity scores <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">[9]</xref>. But real-world preferences are rarely linear. They emerge from complex, indirect relations - co-consumption, influence, social diffusion - that cannot be easily captured in tabular or vectorized form.</p>
<p>This is where graph-based learning offers a paradigm shift. By treating recommendation as a message-passing problem over a structured, non-Euclidean domain, we can better reflect the true nature of user-item interactions. Our work embraces this perspective. We model the MovieLens 100k dataset as a bipartite graph <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">[3]</xref> and employ a GraphSAGE-based GNN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">[10]</xref> to learn directly from this structure. Rather than relying on extensive user metadata or heavy side information, we keep the user nodes minimal - just one-hot encodings of IDs and restrict item nodes to basic semantic features (genres and title embeddings). This allows us to pose a focused research question: when we constrain everything else, can the graph structure alone drive meaningful learning? This design choice echoes recent calls for isolating the effect of graph topology in GNN-based recommender systems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">[11]</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2">
<label>II.</label>
<title>Related Work: Recommender Systems Through a Graph Lens</title>
<p>The journey from similarity heuristics to structural representation learning has reshaped how we design recommendation models. Early collaborative filtering approaches - especially memory-based methods <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">[1]</xref> - were interpretable and simple but struggled under data sparsity or irregular interaction patterns <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">[12]</xref>.</p>
<p>Matrix factorization (MF) techniques <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">[2]</xref>, popularized by the Netflix Prize, shifted focus toward latent embeddings. By mapping users and items into a shared Euclidean space, MF captured hidden preference patterns but treated entities as
<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
<label>Fig. 1.</label>
<caption><p>Between history and state of the art: evolution of recommendation system techniques.</p></caption>
<graphic position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="11273689-fig-1-source.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>isolated vectors - losing sight of the interaction network that connects them.</p>
<p>To address this, a wave of shallow graph embedding methods such as DeepWalk <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">[7]</xref> and Node2Vec <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">[8]</xref> emerged. These techniques sampled paths or neighborhoods in the graph and trained skip-gram models to encode structural proximity. While useful, they were largely unsupervised and decoupled from downstream tasks, limiting their utility in personalized recommendation.</p>
<p>Graph-based recommender models took this further by enabling supervised learning directly on graph structures. Architectures like NGCF <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">[13]</xref>, PinSage <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">[14]</xref>, and GraphSAGE <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">[15]</xref> introduced message passing to capture multi-hop connectivity and higher-order relational signals. These GNN-based models treat recommendation not merely as matrix completion, but as structured prediction over graphs - blending node features, edge semantics, and topology into the learning process.</p>
<p>Recent surveys <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">[15]</xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">[16]</xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">[17]</xref> offer taxonomies of graphbased recommendation techniques, yet few works isolate the structural signal from other data modalities. Our contribution fills this gap: we design an experimental setup that holds everything constant - same dataset, same evaluation metric, same training loop - across classical (MF, CF) and graphbased models. We strip away all user features and only retain minimal movie features (genres + title embeddings). By doing so, we shine light on the core question: to what extent can graph connectivity, as an inductive bias, explain model performance?</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3">
<label>III.</label>
<title>Methodology: from Classical Models to Graph Neural Networks</title>
<p>In order to understand how Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) are capable of revolutionizing recommendation systems, we compare their performance to two classical methods: memorybased Collaborative Filtering (CF) and Matrix Factorization (MF). We test the three methods on the MovieLens 100k dataset. We seek to highlight in which way leveraging graph structure releases a richer modeling bias, unleashing deeper relational patterns in user-item interactions.</p>
<sec id="sec3a">
<label>A.</label>
<title>Problem Formulation: Graph-Based Reframing of Recommendation</title>
<p>The MovieLens 100k dataset contains 100,000 explicit ratings (from 1 to 5) given by 943 users to 1,682 movies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">[3]</xref>. Rather than treating these ratings as isolated entries in a matrix, we reframe the task as a learning problem on a bipartite graph: user nodes on one side, movie nodes on the other, and edges representing observed ratings.</p>
<p>This shift of perspective highlights what really matters: the relationships. Each rating is not just a data point, but part of a broader interaction network. Our objective is to predict missing ratings - turning the task into a regression problem that learns from structure.</p>
<p>We go beyond pure topology by incorporating initial features. Movie nodes are initialized using both their genres (encoded as one-hot vectors) and title embeddings obtained from a pretrained language model. For user nodes, we rely only on their identifiers, represented as one-hot vectors - no additional metadata was considered for them in this study.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref> visualizes this graph, which forms the structural backbone of our GNN-based model
<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
<label>Fig. 2.</label>
<caption><p>Illustration of the bipartite user-item graph. nodes represent users and movies; edges represent observed ratings.</p></caption>
<graphic position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="11273689-fig-2-source.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3b">
<label>B.</label>
<title>Baseline 1: Memory-Based Collaborative Filtering (Cf)</title>
<p>Memory-based CF assumes that similar users will rate items similarly. It calculates similarity between users (or items) using metrics like cosine similarity or Pearson correlation.</p>
<p>The predicted rating <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$\hat{r}_{u, i}$</tex-math></inline-formula> for user <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$u$</tex-math></inline-formula> on item <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$i$</tex-math></inline-formula> is computed as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">[1]</xref>:
<disp-formula id="deqn1"><tex-math notation="LaTeX">\begin{equation*}
\hat{r}_{u, i}=\frac{\sum_{v \in N_{u}} s(u, v) \cdot r_{v, i}}{\sum_{v \in N_{u}}\verts(u, v)\vert}
\tag{1}
\end{equation*}</tex-math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$s(u, v)$</tex-math></inline-formula> is the similarity between users <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$u$</tex-math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$v$</tex-math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$N_{u}$</tex-math></inline-formula> is the set of users similar to <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$u$</tex-math></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>Although intuitive and easy to implement, this method struggles with data sparsity and fails to capture deeper interaction structures.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3c">
<label>C.</label>
<title>Baseline 2: Matrix Factorization (Mf)</title>
<p>MF learns latent vectors for users and items. The rating matrix <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$R$</tex-math></inline-formula> is approximated as the product of two low-rank matrices <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">[2]</xref>:
<disp-formula id="deqn1"><tex-math notation="LaTeX">\begin{equation*}
R \approx P Q^{\top}
\tag{1}
\end{equation*}</tex-math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$P \in \mathbb{R}^{\vertU\vert \times k}$</tex-math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$Q \in \mathbb{R}^{\vertI\vert \times k}$</tex-math></inline-formula>. Each user <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$u$</tex-math></inline-formula> and item <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$i$</tex-math></inline-formula> has a latent vector <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$p_{u}$</tex-math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$q_{i}$</tex-math></inline-formula>, and the predicted rating is:
<disp-formula id="deqn1"><tex-math notation="LaTeX">\begin{equation*}
\hat{r}_{u, i}=p_{u}^{\top} q_{i}
\tag{1}
\end{equation*}</tex-math></disp-formula></p>
<p>MF captures more abstract interactions than CF, but it still treats users and items as independent entities in a latent space, limiting its ability to model relational context.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3d">
<label>D.</label>
<title>Graph Neural Networks for Recommendation</title>
<p>GNNs approach the problem differently. Rather than compressing the data into independent vectors, they model users and items as nodes and propagate information via edges through message passing.</p>
<p>At layer <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$l$</tex-math></inline-formula>, the embedding of node <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$u$</tex-math></inline-formula> is updated by aggregating information from its neighbors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">[4]</xref>:
<disp-formula id="deqn1"><tex-math notation="LaTeX">\begin{equation*}
\begin{aligned}
h_{u}^{(l)}=\sigma &amp; \left(W ^ { (l) } \cdot \operatorname { A G G R E G A T E } \left(\left\{h_{v}^{(l-1)}\right.\right.\right. \\
&amp; \left.\left.: v \in \mathcal{N}(u)\} \cup\left\{h_{u}^{(l-1)}\right\}\right)\right)
\end{aligned}
\tag{1}
\end{equation*}</tex-math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$W^{(l)}$</tex-math></inline-formula> is a learnable weight matrix, <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$\sigma$</tex-math></inline-formula> is a non-linear activation function, and AGGREGATE can be a mean, sum, or max function.</p>
<p>This approach enables GNNs to learn complex, higher-order dependencies that MF and CF typically overlook. It results in richer representations that are aware of graph topology and interaction patterns.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3e">
<label>E.</label>
<title>Model Structure: Graphsage with Mlp for Edge Prediction</title>
<p>We represent user-item interactions with a Graph Neural Network with the GraphSAGE architecture <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">[5]</xref>. As illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">figure 3</xref>, the model initially learns user and item node embeddings solely from their ID. They are then updated by two stacked layers of GraphSAGE convolution, which propagate information from each node&#x0027;s local neighborhood.</p>
<p>Each node embedding is updated using the GraphSAGE update rule:
<disp-formula id="deqn1"><tex-math notation="LaTeX">\begin{equation*}
\begin{aligned}
h_{u}^{(l)}=\sigma &amp; \left(W ^ { (l) } \cdot \operatorname { C O N C A T } \left(h_{u}^{(l-1)},\right.\right. \\
&amp; \left.\left.\operatorname{AGGREGATE}\left(\left\{h_{v}^{(l-1)}: v \in \mathcal{N}(u)\right\}\right)\right)\right)
\end{aligned}
\tag{1}
\end{equation*}</tex-math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$\mathcal{N}(u)$</tex-math></inline-formula> denotes the neighbors of node <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$u, W^{(l)}$</tex-math></inline-formula> is a learnable weight matrix, and <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$\sigma$</tex-math></inline-formula> is a non-linear activation function.</p>
<p>The user and item latent representations are then fed through a Multi-Layer Perceptron (MLP) that predicts the interaction score for each user-item pair-equivalent to the rating in our regression setting. The model is end-to-end trained with mean squared error (MSE) loss.</p>
<p>This architecture allows the network to learn expressive structure-aware representations while preserving the relational inductive bias of the user-item graph. It also allows for more fine-grained predictions than conventional approaches, owing to the inclusion of neighborhood context under message passing.
<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
<label>Fig. 3.</label>
<caption><p>Illustration of the bipartite user-item graph. nodes represent users and movies; edges represent observed ratings.</p></caption>
<graphic position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="11273689-fig-3-source.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4">
<label>IV.</label>
<title>Experimental Setup: Bringing Models to Life</title>
<p>To understand the real-world performance and expressive capacity of our GNN-based recommender system, we design a rigorous experimental setup. This setup mirrors the structure defined in our methodology and allows us to benchmark the proposed model against two classical approaches: Matrix Factorization (MF) and memory-based Collaborative Filtering (CF). All experiments are conducted using the well-established MovieLens 100k dataset <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">[3]</xref>.</p>
<sec id="sec4a">
<label>A.</label>
<title>Dataset and Graph Construction</title>
<p>The MovieLens 100k dataset is 100,000 user-movie ratings given by 943 users on 1,682 movies in a scale from 1 to 5. We represent this data as a bipartite graph: the set of nodes as the users, the set of nodes as the movies, and the edges as the observed ratings. This configuration automatically includes the relational viewpoint that our GNN model will utilize.</p>
<p>Node features. For movie nodes, we construct dense initial embeddings by concatenating genre encodings (onehot vectors) and semantic embeddings of movie titles. We extract the title embeddings using the pretrained all-distilroberta-v1 model from SentenceTransformers. For user nodes, one-hot vectors are utilized based on user IDs only, without side metadata.</p>
<p>This setup ensures that all of the structural cues are derived from the graph itself, rather than from engineered side features. This resulting graph serves as input to our models.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4b">
<label>B.</label>
<title>Model Implementation and Architecture</title>
<p>Our GNN model is implemented using PyTorch Geometric <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">[6]</xref>. The encoder is built using three stacked SAGEConv layers, each followed by ReLU activation. Node embeddings are updated through mean aggregation - the default aggregation function in PyG - enabling information to flow from neighboring nodes.</p>
<p>To adapt the encoder to our heterogeneous graph, we apply to_hetero, which maps the model to a type-aware version. The edge-level decoder combines the user and movie embeddings via concatenation and feeds them into a two-layer MLP that outputs predicted ratings.</p>
<p>The full architecture is trained end-to-end using mean squared error (MSE) loss. Ratings are treated as regression targets, and prediction outputs are later clamped and rounded to lie within the discrete range <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">[5]</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4c">
<label>C.</label>
<title>Training Protocol and Evaluation Metrics</title>
<p>Training for 200 epochs, using the Adam optimizer with a learning rate of 0.01. A ReduceLROnPlateau scheduler is used to adjust the learning rate based on validation performance dynamically.</p>
<p>The data was divided into training, validation, and test sets. via random edge-level splitting (10 &#x0025; for validation and test). No negative sampling is applied, as every rating is explicit.</p>
<p>Model performance is evaluated with Root Mean Squared Error (RMSE) on the predicted ratings. This metric measures the model&#x0027;s capacity to effectively estimate real-valued ratings across all stages of the division.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5">
<title>Baselines:</title>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Collaborative Filtering (CF): We apply item-based CF using both cosine and Pearson similarity metrics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">[1]</xref>. Predictions are computed by weighted averaging and evaluated using RMSE.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Matrix Factorization (MF): We use Truncated Singular Value Decomposition (SVD) with 20 latent components. Predicted ratings result from dot products between user and item vectors.
<p>To ensure fairness, all models are trained and evaluated using the same data splits. This setup helps us fairly quantify the value added by the graph-based inductive bias of GNNs.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6">
<label>V.</label>
<title>Results and Discussion: What the Numbers Tell Us</title>
<p>Now that all models have been trained under consistent conditions, it&#x0027;s time to step back and interpret what we&#x0027;ve learned. Our aim here isn&#x0027;t just to list results, but to reflect on the learning behaviors and the real value each approach brings to the recommendation task.</p>
<sec id="sec6a">
<label>A.</label>
<title>Reading the Rmse Curves</title>
<p>Across the 200 training cycles, we tracked the Root Mean Squared Error (RMSE) across the training, validation, and test datasets. The trajectory of the RMSE, plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>, traces the three stages of learning:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Early Learning (Epochs 0-25): The model learns very quickly, reducing error tremendously. The steep drop reminds the network of its capacity to understand moment-to-moment structure in the set of data.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Refinement and Stabilization (Epochs 25-175): RMS gradually flattening curves, indicating a period of stable refinement. Gradually, the model tends towards maximal representations.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Final Convergence (After Epoch 175): All three RMS curves - training, validation, and test - are kept proximally aligned with each other. Such concordance indicates good generalization and minimal chance of overfitting.
<p>This learning path shows that the GNN architecture has been well-regularized and is helped by the structure that it acquires. The generalizability of the model lies in how it continually performs on unseen validation and test Samples.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
<label>Fig. 4.</label>
<caption><p>Rmse progression across epochs for training, validation, and test sets.</p></caption>
<graphic position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="11273689-fig-4-source.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6b">
<label>B.</label>
<title>Comparing the Models: a Quantitative View</title>
<p>We compared three different models - a Graph Neural Network (GNN), Matrix Factorization (MF), and memorybased Collaborative Filtering (CF) - using RMSE as the evaluation metric. The results are summarized in Table ??.</p>
<p>The GNN model emerges as the clear winner. Its RMSE values remain under 1 across all data splits - an indication that it effectively captures the complex relationships between users and items. The model benefits not only from message passing but also from the node-level feature engineering we applied.</p>
<p>By contrast, MF performs moderately but lacks the expressive power to compete with graph-based learning. It still does better than CF, which appears particularly limited in sparse or
<table-wrap id="table"><label>***</label>
<caption><title></title></caption>
<graphic position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="11273689-table--source.tif"/>
<table rules="all" frame="box" cellpadding="5">
<colgroup>
<col span="4"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Model</th>
<th>Train RMSE</th>
<th>Val RMSE</th>
<th>Test RMSE</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>GNN (GraphSage)</td>
<td>0.9759</td>
<td>0.9883</td>
<td>0.9938</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Matrix Fact</td>
<td>2.1323</td>
<td>&#x2013;</td>
<td>&#x2013;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CF (Cosinus Sim)</td>
<td>3.0027</td>
<td>&#x2013;</td>
<td>&#x2013;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CF (Pearson Sim)</td>
<td>3.0139</td>
<td>&#x2013;</td>
<td>&#x2013;</td>
</tr></tbody>
</table>
<p>\caption[Fig. 5.]{RMSE progression across epochs for training, validation, and test sets.}\label{tbl1}</p>
</table-wrap>
<p>noisy datasets. CF&#x0027;s reliance on similarity heuristics limits its effectiveness here.</p>
<p>C. Looking Beyond the Scores: What Do These Results Tell Us?</p>
<p>Numbers alone don&#x0027;t tell the whole story-but they point us in the right direction. Here&#x0027;s what emerges from this comparative study, both technically and conceptually:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Graph structure changes the game. What truly differentiates GNNs is their capacity to move beyond flat data representations-what we often call Euclidean data, like matrices or grids-and embrace the complexity of non-Euclidean structures such as graphs. By modeling user-item interactions as a network, GNNs don&#x0027;t just predict-they understand. Connectivity becomes a source of inductive bias, allowing the model to detect subtle patterns and generalize more effectively.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Matrix Factorization still holds ground. While it operates in the Euclidean domain, MF can still uncover latent structures and offer solid predictions when data is dense or the graph structure is unavailable. It&#x0027;s efficient, interpretable, and sometimes, that&#x0027;s exactly what&#x0027;s needed in constrained environments.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Collaborative Filtering shows its limits. CF is based on intuitive similarity measures and works well in simpler scenarios. But as soon as the data becomes sparse or noisy-conditions often encountered in real-world sys-tems-its predictive power collapses. It lacks the expressive capacity to model high-order or indirect relationships.
<p>In short, this work illustrates a shift from modeling with surface-level heuristics toward embracing structural awareness. GNNs don&#x0027;t simply memorize patterns-they learn how structure shapes behavior. And that shift, from flat to relational, from isolated to connected, is what makes them such a promising direction for the next generation of recommender systems.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7">
<label>VI.</label>
<title>Conclusion and Future Work: Toward Structure-Aware Recommendations</title>
<p>This study has walked through a comparative journey, starting with classical baselines like Collaborative Filtering and Matrix Factorization, and moving toward a more structure-aware paradigm enabled by Graph Neural Networks. At each step, the message became clearer: when it comes to capturing the nuanced, interconnected nature of user-item interactions, graph-based models offer something qualitatively different.</p>
<p>The GNN architecture we explored doesn&#x0027;t just outperform its predecessors-it shifts the way we frame the recommendation problem. By embedding relational context directly into the learning process it allows us to move beyond flat, tabular representations and toward richer, non-Euclidean learning. The result? A model that generalizes better, adapts to sparse data more gracefully, and captures behavior patterns that other methods miss.</p>
<p>But this is just the beginning.</p>
<p>For future work, several promising directions open up:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Hybrid Feature Integration: While we intentionally minimized metadata usage in this first version, incorporating richer user and content features (e.g., temporal behavior, social signals) could further enhance prediction accuracy.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Hyperbolic and Topological Extensions: Given the hierarchical and latent geometry often found in user-item graphs, extending the model into hyperbolic or topologically-informed spaces may unlock deeper structure.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Explainability and Human-in-the-Loop: One key challenge that remains is interpretability. Future efforts could explore ways to make GNN-based recommendations more transparent and interactive-especially in sensitive domains like healthcare or education.</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2022;</label><p>Scalability to Real-World Datasets: Testing this approach on larger, noisier datasets (such as Amazon, Goodreads, or streaming platforms) would further validate its robustness under real-world constraints.
<p>In closing, this work is not just a performance comparison. It&#x0027;s a call to rethink how we design models that understand people, not as isolated vectors in a matrix, but as dynamic agents embedded in a web of interactions. Graph-based learning gives us the tools to model that web. And with it, perhaps, build recommender systems that are not only more accurate, but also more human-aware.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="ref1"><label>[1]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"> GKIM FALK, Practical Recommender Systems.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref2"><label>[2]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>Y.</given-names> <surname>Koren</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>R.</given-names> <surname>Bell</surname></string-name></person-group>, and <string-name><given-names>C.</given-names>Vol<volume>i</volume>nsky. Matrix factorization techniques for recommender systems. Computer, <volume>42</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>30</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>37</lpage>, <year>2009</year>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ MC.2009.263</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref3"><label>[3]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>F. M.</given-names> <surname>Harper</surname></string-name> and <string-name><given-names>J. A.</given-names> <surname>Konstan</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>The MovieLens Datasets: History and Context</article-title>,&#x201D; <source><italic>ACM Trans. Interact. Intell. Syst.</italic></source>, vol. <volume>5</volume>, no. <issue>4</issue>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>19</lpage>, <year>2015</year>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/2827872</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref4"><label>[4]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>B.</given-names> <surname>Khemani</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>S.</given-names> <surname>Patil</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>K.</given-names> <surname>Kotecha</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>S.</given-names> <surname>Tanwar</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>A review of graph neural networks: concepts, architectures, techniques, challenges, datasets, applications, and future directions</article-title>,&#x201D; <source><italic>IEEE Access</italic></source>, vol. <volume>11</volume>, pp. <fpage>35242</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>35268</lpage>, <year>2023</year>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ACCESS.2023.3264191</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref5"><label>[5]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>W.</given-names> <surname>Hamilton</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Z.</given-names> <surname>Ying</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names> <surname>Leskovec</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>Inductive Representation Learning on Large Graphs</article-title>,&#x201D; in <source>Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)</source>, vol. <volume>30</volume>, <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref6"><label>[6]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>M.</given-names> <surname>Fey</surname></string-name> and <string-name><given-names>J. E.</given-names> <surname>Lenssen</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>Fast Graph Representation Learning with PyTorch Geometric</article-title>,&#x201D; in <source><italic>ICLR Workshop on Representation Learning on Graphs and Manifolds</italic></source>, <year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref7"><label>[7]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"> Grover <etal>et al.</etal> <year>2016</year>. <publisher-loc>node2vec</publisher-loc> : <publisher-name>Scalable Feature Learning for Networks</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref8"><label>[8]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"> Perozzi <etal>et al.</etal> <year>2014</year>. <publisher-loc>DeepWalk</publisher-loc> : <publisher-name>Online Learning of Social Representations</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref9"><label>[9]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>M. M.</given-names> <surname>Bronstein</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names> <surname>Bruna</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Y.</given-names> <surname>LeCun</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A.</given-names> <surname>Szlam</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>P.</given-names> <surname>Vander-</surname></string-name></person-group> gheynst. Geometric deep learning: going beyond euclidean data. IEEE Signal Processing Magazine,<volume>34</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>18</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>42</lpage>, <month>July</month> <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref10"><label>[10]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"> William <string-name><given-names>L.</given-names> <surname>Hamilton</surname></string-name></person-group>, Rex Ying, and Jure Leskovec, Inductive Representation Learning on Large Graphs, Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref11"><label>[11]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="confproc" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>Rex</given-names> <surname>Ying</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Ruining</given-names> <surname>He</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Kaifeng</given-names> <surname>Chen</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Pimwadee</given-names> <surname>Eksombatchai</surname></string-name>, <string-name><surname>William</surname> <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name></person-group> Hamilton, and Jure Leskovec, Graph Convolutional Neural Networks for Web-Scale Recommender Systems, Proceedings of the 24th ACM SIGKDD Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining, pp. <fpage>974</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>983</lpage>, <conf-date>2018</conf-date>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref12"><label>[12]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>W. A.</given-names> <surname>Ali</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>A. M.</given-names> <surname>Shetty</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>M. D. H.</given-names> <surname>Manjaiah</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>A Collaborative Filtering Recommender Systems: Survey</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>Neurocomputing</source>, vol. <volume>513</volume>, pp. <fpage>151</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>170</lpage>, <year>2025</year>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neucom.2024.128718</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref13"><label>[13]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="confproc" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>H.</given-names> <surname>Wang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>M.</given-names> <surname>Zhao</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>W.</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>F. X.</given-names> <surname>Xie</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>M.</given-names> <surname>Wang</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>Neural Graph Collaborative Filtering</article-title>,&#x201D; in <conf-name>Proceedings of the 42nd International ACM SIGIR Conference</conf-name>, <conf-date>2019</conf-date>, pp. <fpage>165</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>174</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/3331184.3331267</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref14"><label>[14]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="confproc" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>R.</given-names> <surname>Ying</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>R.</given-names> <surname>He</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>K.</given-names> <surname>Chen</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>P.</given-names> <surname>Eksombatchai</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>W. L.</given-names> <surname>Hamilton</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names> <surname>Leskovec</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>Graph Convolutional Neural Networks for Web-Scale Recommender Systems</article-title>,&#x201D; in <conf-name>Proceedings of the 24th ACM SIGKDD</conf-name>, <conf-date>2018</conf-date>, pp. <fpage>974</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>983</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/3219819.3219890</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref15"><label>[15]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>S.</given-names> <surname>Wu</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>F.</given-names> <surname>Sun</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>W.</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>B.</given-names> <surname>Cui.</surname></string-name></person-group> Graph neural networks in recommender systems: a survey,<year>2021</year>. arXiv: 2011.02260 [cs.IR]</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref16"><label>[16]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>C.</given-names> <surname>Gao</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Y.</given-names> <surname>Zheng</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>N.</given-names> <surname>Li</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Y.</given-names> <surname>Li</surname></string-name></person-group>, <string-name><given-names>Y.</given-names> <surname>Gin</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names> <surname>Piao</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Y.</given-names> <surname>Quan</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names> <surname>Chang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>D.</given-names> <surname>Jin</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>X.</given-names> <surname>He</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>Y.</given-names> <surname>Li</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>A Survey of Graph Neural Networks for Recommender Systems: Challenges, Methods, and Directions</article-title>,&#x201D; <source specific-use="IEEE">IEEE Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering</source>, vol. <volume>36</volume>, no. <issue>1</issue>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>25</lpage>, <year>2024</year>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TKDE.2023.3240917</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref17"><label>[17]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>H.</given-names> <surname>Wang</surname></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Y.</given-names> <surname>Zhang</surname></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>J.</given-names> <surname>Wang</surname></string-name></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>A Survey on Graph Neural Networks for Recommender Systems</article-title>,&#x201D; <source specific-use="IEEE">IEEE Access</source>, vol. <volume>10</volume>, pp. <fpage>93794</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>93818</lpage>, <year>2022</year>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ACCESS.2022.3207339</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>

</back>
</conf-article>