<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE conf-article PUBLIC "-//IEEE//IEEE Conferences JATS-based DTD v2.0//EN" "conferences.dtd">
<conf-article article-type="research" content-type="orig-research" dtd-version="2.0" open-access="no" xml:lang="eng" show-flag="show" peer-reviewed="yes" lifecycle="final" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<!-- Article Processing Date: 12/05/2025 -->
<!-- Vendor Name: Aptara -->
<!-- IEEE XML JATS Tagging Guidelines version: 20241024 -->
<!-- IEEE Math Coding Requirements and Guidelines for Vendors version: v2.4 -->
<conf-front>
<conf-proc-meta>
<conf-proc-id conf-proc-id-type="conf-acronym">EE&#x0026;AE</conf-proc-id>
<conf-proc-title-group>
<conf-full-title>2025 10th International Conference on Energy Efficiency and Agricultural Engineering (EE&#x0026;AE)</conf-full-title>
<conf-normalized-title>Energy Efficiency and Agricultural Engineering (EE&#x0026;AE), 2025 10th International Conference on</conf-normalized-title>
</conf-proc-title-group>
<volume>00</volume>
<isbn publication-format="electronic">979-8-3315-1299-6</isbn>
</conf-proc-meta>
<conf-meta>
<conf-name>2025 10th International Conference on Energy Efficiency and Agricultural Engineering (EE&#x0026;AE)</conf-name>
<conf-start iso-8601-date="2025-11-05"><day>05</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></conf-start>
<conf-end iso-8601-date="2025-11-07"><day>07</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></conf-end>
<conf-loc><city>Stara Zagora</city>, <country>Bulgaria</country></conf-loc>
</conf-meta>
<conf-article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/EEAE65901.2025.11273791</article-id>
<xplore-article-id>11273791</xplore-article-id>
<xplore-issue>11273194</xplore-issue>
<xplore-pub-id>11273191</xplore-pub-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Technical Privacy Risks in Generative Ai (Genai)Lessons From Owasp and Real-World Failures</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
<name-alternatives>
<string-name specific-use="display"><given-names>Elitsa</given-names> <surname>Kuzmanova</surname></string-name>
<string-name specific-use="index"><given-names>Elitsa</given-names> <surname>Kuzmanova</surname></string-name>
</name-alternatives>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
<name-alternatives>
<string-name specific-use="display"><given-names>Donika</given-names> <surname>Dimanova</surname></string-name>
<string-name specific-use="index"><given-names>Donika</given-names> <surname>Dimanova</surname></string-name>
</name-alternatives>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution content-type="institution">Konstantin Preslavsky University of Shumen \\ Shumen</institution>
</institution-wrap>
, <country>Bulgaria</country> \\ <email>elitsa.yurieva@gmail.com</email></aff>
<aff id="aff2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution content-type="institution">Konstantin Preslavsky University of Shumen \\ Shumen</institution>
</institution-wrap>
, <country>Bulgaria</country> \\ <email>d.dimanova@shu.bg</email></aff>
<pub-date date-type="cover" pub-type="print" iso-8601-date="2025-11-07"><day>7</day><month>Nov.</month><year>2025</year></pub-date>
<fpage>***</fpage>
<lpage>***</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>979-8-3315-1299-6 &#x00A9; 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining, and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See <uri>https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html</uri> for more information.</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2025</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder copyright-owner="IEEE"></copyright-holder>
<license license-type="IEEE">
<ali:license_ref></ali:license_ref>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="xml">11273791_ft.xml</self-uri>
<self-uri content-type="print">72.pdf</self-uri>
<abstract xml:lang="en">
<p>The rapid deployment of generative Artificial Intelligence (GenAI) systems has introduced a new class of technical privacy risks that exceed the scope of traditional data protection frameworks. This paper investigates these emerging vulnerabilities through the lens of the OWASP Top 10 for Large Language Models (LLMs) - 2025 edition, correlating them with real-world privacy failures from <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$2023-2025$</tex-math></inline-formula>. It categorizes incidents such as prompt injection, model poisoning, excessive agency, and improper output handling, drawing connections between architectural design choices and user-level data exposure. High-profile cases - including OpenAI&#x0027;s GDPR fine by Italy&#x0027;s Garante, the Hugging Face transformer compromise, and the Reddit-Anthropic dispute illustrate the systemic nature of GenAI risks. In parallel, the study evaluates international regulatory and governance responses, including the EU AI Act, NIST AI RMF, ISO/IEC 42001, and China&#x0027;s algorithmic controls, highlighting their strengths and implementation gaps. The analysis reveals that technical vulnerabilities often cascade across the GenAI lifecycle, creating enforcement blind spots and compliance challenges. The paper concludes by advocating for a holistic, cross-functional risk management strategy that integrates secure-by-design principles, real-time oversight, and proactive alignment with evolving regulatory standards.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="AuthorFree">
<kwd>GenerativeAI</kwd>
<kwd>Technical privacy risks</kwd>
<kwd>OWASP</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="0"/>
<table-count count="3"/>
<equation-count count="0"/>
<ref-count count="19"/>
<page-count count="0"/>
</counts>
</conf-article-meta>
</conf-front><pt><front>
\DeclareUnicodeCharacter{20AC}{\ifmmode\text{\euro}\else\euro\fi}
</front></pt>
<body>
<sec id="sec1">
<label>I.</label>
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>In December 2024, Italy&#x0027;s data protection authority, Garante per la Protezione dei Dati Personali, imposed a 15 million euro fine on OpenAI - the first penalty of its kind against a generative AI provider - for violations of the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR). The decision originates from an ex officio investigation initiated following the publication of press-reports regarding a data breach that occurred on March 2023. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">[1]</xref> Concerns included the absence of a valid legal basis for processing personal data, inadequate transparency in data handling, and insufficient safeguards for minors. This landmark enforcement - complemented by a mandated six-month public awareness campaign - signals the growing confrontation between rapid AI innovation and privacy safeguards. It highlights pervasive vulnerabilities in how Generative Artificial Intelligence (GenAI) systems harvest and handle personal data.</p>
<p>While previous studies have focused primarily on ethical and legal implications by authors like Feuerriegel et al., 2024 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">[2]</xref> and Golda et al., 2024 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">[5]</xref>, comparatively little attention has been given to the technical foundations of these risks how specific system vulnerabilities enable privacy breaches in real-world applications. Recent research of Lyu et al., 2025 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">[19]</xref> has begun to systematize the understanding of such risks by mapping privacy attacks across the large language model (LLM) lifecycle, yet the connection between these technical vulnerabilities and regulatory or governance frameworks remains underexplored. This gap underscores the need for systematic analysis linking the technical characteristics of GenAI systems to their compliance, accountability, and oversight implications.</p>
<p>Accordingly, this study examines the evolving landscape of technical privacy risks in generative AI by analyzing incidents reported between 2023 and 2025 and aligning them with established security taxonomies such as the Open Worldwide Application Security Project (OWASP) Top 10 for Large Language Models (LLMs). By correlating these vulnerabilities with high-profile privacy failures and evaluating the corresponding international governance responses - particularly the European Union Artificial Intelligence Act (EU AI Act), the National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) Artificial Intelligence Risk Management Framework (AI RMF), and the International Organization for Standardization - International Electrotechnical Commission (ISO/IEC) 42001 - the paper aims to identify the structural weaknesses that perpetuate enforcement gaps.</p>
<p>The overarching objective is to contribute to a more integrated understanding of GenAI privacy risks, bridging the divide between technical security practices and regulatory expectations, and supporting the development of secure-bydesign, accountable AI systems.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2">
<label>II.</label>
<title>Architecturial Foundations of Generative Ai (Gen Ai)</title>
<p>The roots of artificial intelligence (AI) trace back to mid20th century philosophical and computational ideas, including Alan Turing&#x0027;s seminal exploration "Computing Machinery and Intelligence" and the Dartmouth Conference of 1956 organized by John McCarthy and Marvin Minsky. These developments formally established AI as a scientific field. Early symbolic reasoning systems such as ELIZA (1966) marked the nascent stages of computer-based language simulation. The 1980s saw renewed interest in neural networks, though progress was impeded by computational limitations and periods of reduced funding-often referred to as "AI winters." Despite these challenges, momentum returned in the 1990s and early 2000s as machine learning methods matured.</p>
<p>Most notably, the introduction of AlexNet in 2012 revolutionized image recognition and heralded the era of deep learning. Further breakthroughs followed with the publication of the transformer architecture in 2017, enabling efficient and scalable sequence modeling via self-attention. These advancements set the stage for large language models (LLMs)</p>
<p>such as GPT 3 and GPT 4, with increasingly powerful generative capabilities.</p>
<p>The advent of Generative AI (GenAI) represents a transformative leap: systems capable of synthesizing novel content-text, images, or audio-from learned data distributions. Unlike conventional AI, which focuses on classification or prediction, GenAI utilizes architectures such as Variational Autoencoders (VAEs), Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs), autoregressive transformer-based models, and diffusion models like Stable Diffusion, often trained on massive, minimally curated datasets. These architectural innovations have enabled unprecedented generative fidelity, and by 2025 models like GPT 4 and Gemini 2.0 are empowering enterprises to scale content creation, automate workflows, and personalize experiences. These systems have introduced novel privacy challenges-including emergent memorization and contextual inference-that transcend traditional governance frameworks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">[2]</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3">
<label>III.</label>
<title>Technical Privacy Risks in Gen Ai</title>
<p>As Generative AI systems are deployed across consumer applications and enterprise environments, the complexity and severity of privacy risks have intensified. These risks are predominantly technical in nature, arising from the structural properties of Large Language Models (LLM) and their dependence on massive datasets, sophisticated architectures, and real-time inferencing. Unlike traditional rule-based systems, generative models are trained on heterogeneous, often unvetted corpora, and exhibit emergent behaviors that challenge established data governance norms. Such behaviors include hallucination, unauthorized memorization, and autonomous content generation, all of which pose risks to user privacy and data integrity.</p>
<p>The Stanford AI Index 2025 reports a 56.4&#x0025; increase in AI-related incidents in 2024, totaling 233 reported casesmany of which involve privacy breaches such as deepfake generation, unauthorized data scraping, and inadvertent personal data exposure. While this trend demonstrates the accelerating privacy threat landscape, it also likely underestimates the true scale of the problem due to underreporting and reliance on media coverage (3). A Privacy and Security Concerns in Generative AI: A Comprehensive Survey identifies five intersecting lenses for evaluating GenAI risks - user, ethical, legal, technological, and institutional <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">[5]</xref> yet technical analysis remains the most underexplored in current governance literature.</p>
<p>To contextualize the technical nature of these risks, it is essential to refer to structured security frameworks that specifically address vulnerabilities in large language models. The Open Worldwide Application Security Project (OWASP) - a globally recognized non-profit foundation established in 2001 and dedicated to improving software security through open, community-driven initiatives - develops free, consensus-based standards and methodologies used worldwide by developers, auditors, and regulators. Its projects aim to increase visibility into the most critical security issues across technologies and to promote best practices for mitigating them. Among its most widely adopted outputs is the "Top 10" series, which identifies the most prevalent and impactful categories of software vulnerabilities based on empirical data and expert analysis. In 2025, OWASP released the Top 10 for Large Language Model (LLM) Applications, a dedicated framework addressing security and privacy risks unique to generative AI systems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">[4]</xref>. This taxonomy was developed collaboratively by more than 500 contributors from academia, industry, and regulatory bodies, drawing from realworld incidents, red-team assessments, and empirical evidence.</p>
<p>The OWASP Top 10 for LLMs (2025 edition) offers a structured and technical taxonomy of such risks, drawing from community consensus and empirical incidents collected in 2024-2025. The taxonomy reflects risks such as prompt injection, insecure output handling, training data poisoning, model denial of service, plugin insecurities, and model theft. These risks do not exist in isolation; they are systemically embedded into the GenAI lifecycle, from model training and deployment to integration in external environments. Each threat reveals how privacy breaches can occur through vulnerabilities in prompt logic, data provenance, architectural permissions, or model behavior, with implications for both organizational compliance and end-user harm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">[4]</xref>.
<table-wrap id="table1">
<label>Table I:</label>
<caption><title>2025 owasp top 10 list for llm and gen ai (4)</title></caption>
<graphic position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="11273791-table-1-source.tif"/>
<table rules="all" frame="box" cellpadding="5">
<colgroup>
<col span="3"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Risk ID</th>
<th>Risk</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>LLM01 -25</td>
<td>Prompt Injection</td>
<td>Manipulating LLMs through crafted inputs that override system prompts or exploit external inputs to cause unintended actions.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LLM02 -25</td>
<td>Sensitive Information Disclosure</td>
<td>Exposure of personally identifiable information, financial, health, business, or legal data through LLM responses or inference.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LLM03 -25</td>
<td>Supply Chain</td>
<td>Vulnerabilities in training data, thirdparty models, and platforms that lead to bias, breaches, or model failure.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LLM04 -25</td>
<td>Data and Model Poisoning</td>
<td>Injecting malicious data during pretraining, fine-tuning, or embedding stages to introduce vulnerabilities or backdoors into the model.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LLM05 -25</td>
<td>Improper Output Handling</td>
<td>Failure to validate or sanitize LLM outputs, enabling injection attacks like XSS, CSRF, or privilege escalation.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LLM06 -25</td>
<td>Excessive Agency</td>
<td>Granting LLMs dynamic decisionmaking powers through tools or plugins that may lead to uncontrolled actions.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LLM07 -25</td>
<td>System Prompt Leakage</td>
<td>Unintentional disclosure of system prompts containing sensitive or behavioral instructions, allowing attackers to infer or exploit them.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LLM08 -25</td>
<td>Vector and Embedding Weaknesses</td>
<td>Exploits in vector generation, storage, or retrieval pipelines-especially in retrieval-augmented generation (RAG)-can allow injection or data leakage.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LLM09 -25</td>
<td>Misinformation</td>
<td>Generation of false or misleading outputs that can harm trust, reputation, or lead to legal liabilities.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LLM10 -25</td>
<td>Unbounded Consumption</td>
<td>Resource exhaustion vulnerabilities due to LLMs consuming or generating large, uncontrolled outputs that degrade performance or leak information through inference</td>
</tr></tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4">
<label>IV.</label>
<title>Risk Categorization and Mapping to Real World Examples</title>
<p>Privacy risks in generative AI systems manifest through specific technical vulnerabilities that are increasingly visible in real-world deployments. The OWASP 2025 Top 10 framework provides a valuable lens for identifying and analyzing these incidents. These risks are not isolated but interdependent, often cascading across system layers. The following categorization synthesizes real-world incidents aligned with OWASP 2025 classifications.</p>
<sec id="sec4a">
<label>A.</label>
<title>Data Exposure and Integrity Risks</title>
<p>Privacy risks from unintended data exposure and compromised integrity are prevalent in GenAI. LLM06: Excessive Agency addresses the risk of overly autonomous models performing unauthorized actions, potentially exposing sensitive data due to excessive permissions or functionality. LLM04: Data and Model Poisoning compounds this by enabling malicious data manipulation to corrupt outputs, risking private information disclosure.</p>
<p>The OpenAI ChatGPT macOS App Vulnerability (July 2024) illustrates this, where plain-text storage of user conversations risked sensitive data exposure, prompting an encryption update by OpenAI. This incident is listed in the National Vulnerability Database as CVE-2024-40594. Additional cases include the PoisonGPT experiment, in which manipulated web content was used to insert misinformation and backdoors into open-source models, demonstrating the real-world feasibility of data poisoning attacks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">[6]</xref>. Similarly, Hugging Face (2025) reported a security issue involving politically manipulated fine-tuned models that highlighted inadequate validation processes in hosted content <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">[7]</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4b">
<label>B.</label>
<title>Manipulation and Explotation Risks</title>
<p>GenAI systems are susceptible to privacy breaches through manipulation or exploitation. LLM01: Prompt Injection allows attackers to manipulate inputs, disclosing sensitive data or generating unauthorized content. LLM10: Unbounded Consumption heightens this risk, where excessive or malicious queries can expose data via resource strain.</p>
<p>In December 2024, Italy&#x0027;s data protection authority (Garante) imposed a <inline-formula><tex-math notation="LaTeX">$&#x20AC; 15$</tex-math></inline-formula> million fine on OpenAI for GDPR violations after user prompts were found to inadvertently expose conversation data of other users <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">[8]</xref>. Microsoft&#x0027;s Bing Copilot (2024) faced a series of incidents involving prompt injection attacks generating harmful or politically biased content <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">[9]</xref>. Additionally, in 2025, a major European bank experienced recursive prompt loops in its GenAI-based customer service chatbot, resulting in the unintentional disclosure of sensitive client data and a temporary service outage <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">[10]</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4c">
<label>C.</label>
<title>Operational and Systematic Risks</title>
<p>These risks stem from design flaws, third-party dependencies, and insufficient monitoring. LLM03: Supply Chain Vulnerabilities highlight the risk of untrusted datasets or plugins, potentially enabling data exfiltration or model corruption. LLM05: Improper Output Handling aggregates risk from unsanitized LLM outputs that lead to downstream security issues.</p>
<p>The Reddit vs. Anthropic case (June 2025) involves allegations of unauthorized data scraping used to train Claude AI, raising questions about supply chain due diligence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">[11]</xref>. The ChatGPT iOS plugin cache leak (January 2025) revealed cached plugin data containing sensitive content, illustrating improper output handling. Also in 2025, a compromised transformer uploaded to Hugging Face&#x0027;s repository disguised itself as a legitimate model and passed malware payloads to downstream systems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">[12]</xref>.</p>
<p>The interconnectivity of these risks is evident. The OpenAI macOS vulnerability (LLM06) exposed consumer data and triggered regulatory scrutiny tied to exploitation (LLM01), illustrating how operational failures cascade across the AI lifecycle. The Anthropic case reflects systemic supply chain lapses (LLM03), emphasizing the need for more rigorous data provenance controls. Similarly, the OpenAI GDPR fine resulted from prompt exploitation (LLM10), underscoring the critical importance of secure input validation.
<table-wrap id="table2"><label>TABII</label>
<caption><title>Le ii: summary of representative incidents mapped to owasp 2025 risk categories</title></caption>
<graphic position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="11273791-table-2-source.tif"/>
<table rules="all" frame="box" cellpadding="5">
<colgroup>
<col span="3"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>OWASP Risk Category</th>
<th>Representative Real-World Incident (2023 2025)</th>
<th>Observed Privacy / Compliance Impact</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>LLM04 - Data and Model Poisoning / LLM06 Excessive Agency</td>
<td>OpenAI ChatGPT macOS App Vulnerability (2024); PoisonGPT Experiment (2024); Hugging Face FineTuned Model Incident (2025)</td>
<td>Unencrypted local data and malicious training content caused unintended exposure (CVE-2024-40594) and demonstrated the feasibility of data-poisoning and agency-overreach attacks.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LLM01 Prompt Injection / LLM10 Unbounded Consumption</td>
<td>OpenAI GDPR Fine (Italy Garante 2024); Microsoft Bing Copilot Prompt Abuse (2024); European Bank Chatbot Loop (2025)</td>
<td>Crafted prompts and recursive queries led to cross-user data leaks, biased outputs, and service outages, resulting in regulatory sanctions and reputational damage.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LLM03 Supply Chain Vulnerabilities / LLM05 Improper Output Handling</td>
<td>Reddit vs Anthropic (2025); ChatGPT iOS Plugin Cache Leak (2025); Hugging Face Transformer Compromise (2025)</td>
<td>Unauthorized data scraping, unsanitized plugin outputs, and infected model artifacts exposed sensitive information, highlighting supply-chain and validation weaknesses in GenAI ecosystems.</td>
</tr></tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5">
<label>V.</label>
<title>Regulatory and Governance Response</title>
<p>The proliferation of GenAI technologies has outpaced the capacity of traditional regulatory mechanisms, revealing blind spots in data protection, accountability, and risk oversight. As illustrated by the complex and interconnected risks outlined in the previous section, organizations are grappling with vulnerabilities that span data leakage, prompt exploitation, supply chain fragility, and ungoverned model behaviors. These challenges cannot be mitigated by technical controls alone - they require governance structures that align legal obligations with operational and security frameworks.</p>
<p>A patchwork of international efforts is emerging in response. Different jurisdictions are adopting various approaches to AI regulation. In some regions, regulators have opted for a proactive stance, enacting comprehensive legislation designed to preempt potential risks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">[13]</xref>.</p>
<p>In the European Union, the AI Act (Regulation (EU) 2024/1689), which came into force on 1 August 2024, marks the world&#x0027;s first binding horizontal regulation on AI. Full enforcement is expected by 2026. It introduces tiered risk classifications for AI systems and mandates conformity assessments, transparency disclosures, and governance mechanisms for general-purpose and high-risk AI systems. The General-Purpose AI Code of Practice, published by the EU AI Office in July 2025, serves as an interim instrument to prepare providers for compliance and includes commitments around transparency, data provenance, and safety auditing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">[18]</xref>.</p>
<p>In the United States, federal AI governance has evolved through executive action. Executive Order 14110, issued in October 2023, had required federal agencies to appoint Chief AI Officers and implement the NIST AI RMF. However, in January 2025, Executive Order 13179 repealed these mandates, reflecting a strategic pivot toward innovation, interoperability, and voluntary risk management <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">[15]</xref>. The resulting governance vacuum has been partially filled by sector-specific initiatives and voluntary adoption of standards.</p>
<p>Among the most widely adopted frameworks is the NIST AI Risk Management Framework (1.0), which remains foundational for U.S.-based organizations. As of 2025, NIST is collaborating with private sector stakeholders to refine implementation profiles for high-risk domains including healthcare, finance, and critical infrastructure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">[16]</xref>. Meanwhile, ISO/IEC 42001:2023 for Artificial Intelligence System Management (AISM) continues to gain traction in regulated industries, though no updated version has been released in 2025. Its certifiability has made it attractive in banking, insurance, and pharmaceuticals, particularly where synergies exist with established ISO/IEC standards.</p>
<p>Outside the EU and U.S., China&#x0027;s Interim Measures on Generative AI, in effect since August 2023, mandate algorithm registration, output watermarking, and security assessments. In early 2025, China&#x0027;s Cyberspace Administration advanced proposals for an expanded governance regime that emphasizes accountability, traceability, and alignment with state ideology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">[17]</xref>. Meanwhile, the Council of Europe is finalizing its Convention on Artificial Intelligence, Human Rights, Democracy and the Rule of Law, anticipated for adoption in late 2025. Canada&#x0027;s Artificial Intelligence and Data Act (AIDA) is undergoing revision to integrate GenAI-specific provisions.</p>
<p>In the UK, sector-specific regulatory guidance continues to evolve under the Department for Science, Innovation and Technology.</p>
<p>Despite these developments, several challenges remain. Many frameworks lack provisions for real-time oversight and output integrity assurance, particularly for generative models exhibiting autonomous behaviors. Jurisdictional fragmentation further complicates cross-border compliance, and voluntary standards, while flexible, require considerable institutional investment and technical expertise for effective deployment. As GenAI systems become more sophisticated, governance models must adapt to address runtime risks, emergent behavior, and global data flows.
<table-wrap id="table3">
<label>Table III:</label>
<caption><title>Comparative overview of ai governance frameworks (as of 2025)</title></caption>
<graphic position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="11273791-table-3-source.tif"/>
<table rules="all" frame="box" cellpadding="5">
<colgroup>
<col span="3"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Framework / Jurisdiction</th>
<th>Key Features</th>
<th>Coverage &#x0026; Gaps for Technical Privacy Risks</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>EU AI Act (Reg. 2024/1689)</td>
<td>In force Aug 2024; full enforcement 2026. Tiered risk system, conformity checks, transparency, dataprovenance duties; 2025 Code of Practice adds interim guidance.</td>
<td>Strong on governance and disclosure; weak on runtime control and cross-border enforcement.</td>
</tr></tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table rules="all" frame="box" cellpadding="5">
<colgroup>
<col span="3"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>U.S. Executive Orders 14110 (2023) &#x0026; 13179 (2025)</th>
<th>14110 mandated AI Officers &#x0026; NIST AI RMF; 13179 repealed mandates - voluntary, innovation-driven approach.</th>
<th>Fragmented oversight; depends on sector adoption of NIST AI RMF.</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>NIST AI Risk Management Framework (1.0)</td>
<td>Voluntary lifecycle-risk guidance; profiles in development for highrisk sectors.</td>
<td>Broad technical guidance but no certification or mandatory runtime monitoring.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ISO/IEC 42001:2023 (AISMS)</td>
<td>Certifiable AImanagement standard; adopted in regulated sectors.</td>
<td>Strong organizational controls; limited focus on LLM-specific vulnerabilities.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>China - Interim Measures (2023)</td>
<td>Algorithm registration, watermarking, security reviews; 2025 draft adds accountability rules.</td>
<td>Addresses content integrity; enforcement transparency remains limited.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Council of Europe AI Convention</td>
<td>Human-rights-based treaty (expected 2025); coordination across states.</td>
<td>Normative only-no operational or technical provisions.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Canada - AIDA (2025 draft)</td>
<td>Revising to add GenAI risk classification and oversight.</td>
<td>Direction aligned with EU Act; technical controls pending.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>UK - Sectoral Guidance</td>
<td>"Pro-innovation" model led by DSIT; domain regulators issue AI rules.</td>
<td>Flexible but fragmented; lacks unified runtime oversight.</td>
</tr></tbody>
</table>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6">
<label>VI.</label>
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>As generative AI continues to advance in capability and scope, the resulting privacy risks are evolving in both technical sophistication and systemic reach. This paper has explored how foundational vulnerabilities-categorized under the OWASP Top 10 for LLMs-are not merely theoretical risks but are already manifesting through realworld failures. From prompt injection and improper output handling to systemic agency overreach and data poisoning, GenAI privacy breaches are undermining user trust, exposing organizations to regulatory scrutiny, and posing novel governance challenges.</p>
<p>Although international regulatory frameworks, including the EU AI Act, NIST AI RMF, ISO/IEC 42001, and China&#x0027;s generative AI measures, signal progress in aligning governance with emerging AI risks, significant gaps persist. These include fragmented oversight, insufficient real-time enforcement mechanisms, and the resource-intensive nature of compliance with voluntary standards. The interconnectivity of technical vulnerabilities and regulatory fragmentation underscores the need for holistic, cross-functional risk management approaches that embed security and privacy-bydesign throughout the AI lifecycle.</p>
<p>Ultimately, mitigating technical privacy risks in generative AI will require a coordinated response across technical, organizational, and legal domains. Bridging the current gaps between governance expectations and technical implementations must become a priority for regulators, developers, and corporate leaders alike if generative AI is to evolve in a secure, trustworthy, and ethically responsible direction.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack><title>Acknowledgment</title>
<p>The author gratefully acknowledge the support provided by the project CoE UNITe BG16RFPR002-1.014-0004 funded by PRIDST, co-funded by the European Union. This study was supported by internal research project RD-08-</p>
<p>109/05.02.2025 funded by Konstantin Preslavsky University of Shumen.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="ref1"><label>[1]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chiara</surname>, <given-names>P. G.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x201C;<article-title>Italy. Italian DPA Fines OpenAI for GDPR Non Compliance: The Last Episode of the Garante - OpenAI Saga</article-title>,&#x201D;? European Data Protection Law Review, <volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <year>2025</year>, <fpage>102</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>108</lpage>. <uri>https://doi.org/10.21552/edpl/2025/1/17</uri></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref2"><label>[2]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Feuerriegel</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal> &#x201C;<article-title>Generative A<string-name><given-names>I.</given-names> <surname>Business</surname></string-name></person-group> &#x0026; Information Systems Engineering</article-title>,&#x201D; <volume>66</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <year>2024</year>, <fpage>111</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>126</lpage>. <uri>https://doi.org/10.1007/s12599-023-00834-7</uri></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref3"><label>[3]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="report" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>Standford</given-names> <surname>University</surname></string-name></person-group>, The <year>2025</year> AI Index Report The <year>2025</year> AI Index Report \vert Stanford HAI.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref4"><label>[4]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="other"> Official OWASP Website - OWASP Top 10 for Large Language Model Applications \vert OWASP Foundation</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref5"><label>[5]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>A.</given-names> <surname>Golda</surname></string-name> <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>, &#x201C;<article-title>Privacy and Security Concerns in Generative AI: A Comprehensive Survey</article-title>,&#x201D; in <source specific-use="IEEE">IEEE Access</source>, vol. <volume>12</volume>, pp. <fpage>48126</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>48144</lpage>, <year>2024</year>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ACCESS.2024.3381611</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref6"><label>[6]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Miller</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, &#x0026; <string-name><surname>Ribeiro</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x201C;<article-title>PoisonGPT: How to Backdoor LLMs via Malicious Web Content</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>arXiv preprint</source> arXiv:<pub-id pub-id-type="arxiv">2403.12147</source>, <year>2024</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref7"><label>[7]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="online" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"> Hugging Face.</person-group> &#x201C;<article-title>Incident Report: Politically Biased Fine-Tuned Model Upload</article-title>,&#x201D; <year>2025</year>, <uri>https://huggingface.co/blog/security-2025</uri></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref8"><label>[8]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="online" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"> Garante per la Protezione dei Dati Personali.</person-group> &#x201C;<article-title>OpenAI fined &#x20AC;15 million for GDPR breaches</article-title>,&#x201D; <year>2024</year>, <uri>https://www.garanteprivacy.it/home/docweb/-/docwebdisplay/docweb/9999999</uri></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref9"><label>[9]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Khan</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name>, &#x0026; <string-name><surname>Shoaib</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x201C;<article-title>Prompt Injection Attacks on Microsoft Copilot: A Case Analysis. International Journal of Cybersecurity</article-title>,&#x201D; <volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <year>2024</year>, <fpage>210</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>219</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref10"><label>[10]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="online" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>European</given-names> <surname>Banking</surname></string-name></person-group> Federation. AI Risk Management in Financial Services, <year>2025</year>, <uri>https://www.ebf.eu/publications/ai-risk-2025/</uri></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref11"><label>[11]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="online" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"> Reuters.</person-group> &#x201C;<article-title>Reddit Sues Anthropic Over Data Scraping for Claude AI</article-title>,&#x201D; <year>2025</year>, <uri>https://www.reuters.com/technology/reddit-sues-anthropic2025/</uri></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref12"><label>[12]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="online" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"> OWASP Foundation.</person-group> &#x201C;<article-title>Supply Chain Threat Report: Transformer Model Compromise</article-title>,&#x201D; <year>2025</year>, <uri>https://owasp.org/projects/genai-threatintel/</uri></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref13"><label>[13]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ayebo</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x201C;<article-title>Comparative Legal Responses to Generative AI: A Global Governance Perspective</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>Journal of Law and Emerging Technologies</source>, <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <year>2025</year>, <fpage>56</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref14"><label>[14]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"> European Commission.</person-group> &#x201C;<article-title>Regulation (EU) <year>2024</year>/1689 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 13 <month>June</month> <year>2024</year> on Artificial Intelligence</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>Official Journal of the European Union</source>, <year>2024</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref15"><label>[15]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="online" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><given-names>The</given-names> <surname>White</surname></string-name></person-group> House. &#x201C;<article-title>Executive Order 13179 - Innovation and Interoperability in Artificial Intelligence</article-title>,&#x201D; <year>2025</year>, Retrieved from <uri>https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefing-room/presidential-actions/2025/01/10/executive-order-13179/</uri></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref16"><label>[16]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="online" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"> NIST.</person-group> &#x201C;<article-title>AI Risk Management Framework - Implementation Profiles and Sector Applications</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>National Institute of Standards and Technology</source>, <year>2025</year>, Retrieved from <uri>https://www.nist.gov/itl/ai-risk-management-framework</uri></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref17"><label>[17]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="periodical" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wei</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names></string-name>, &#x0026; <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group> &#x201C;<article-title>Reinforcing State Control: China&#x0027;s Expanding Generative AI Governance Model</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>Journal of Cyber Policy</source>, <volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <year>2025</year>, <fpage>42</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref18"><label>[18]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="online" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Krause</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names></string-name> &#x201C;<article-title>The EU AI Act and the Future of AI Governance: Implications for <string-name><given-names>U.S.</given-names> <surname>Firms</surname></string-name></person-group> and Policymakers</article-title>,&#x201D; <source>SSRN Working Paper</source>, <year>2025</year>, Retrieved from <uri>https://ssrn.com/abstract=4752282</uri></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="ref19"><label>[19]</label> <mixed-citation publication-type="online" publication-format="print"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lyu</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names></string-name>, &#x0026; <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names></string-name></person-group> SoK: Semantic Privacy in Large Language Models, <year>2025</year>, arXiv preprint <uri>https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2506.23603</uri></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>

</back>
</conf-article>